<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Way to peace, by the proposal of some considerations arguing the necessity of mutual love, and forbearance in many things to effect it</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F64</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12039007</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12039007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52929)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 67:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Way to peace, by the proposal of some considerations arguing the necessity of mutual love, and forbearance in many things to effect it</title>
                  <author>T. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Strange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: T.F.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peace --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52929:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52929:1"/>
            <p>THE WAY TO PEACE, By the Propoſal of ſome CONSIDERATIONS ARGUING THE NECESSITY OF MUTUAL LOVE; AND FORBEARANCE in many THINGS, To Effect It.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Strange.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52929:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Diſcourſe, though it may ſerve for any Meridian the Chriſtian World, yet is it more particularly calculate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for this <hi>Famous City,</hi> to which as a Native and Memb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I am related; and in whoſe Peace and Proſperity my ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is involved. The occaſion that moved me to theſe Conſiderations, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what eſcapes few Mens notice and complaints; <hi>viz.</hi> our <hi>Indecent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions</hi> and <hi>Rough Deportment</hi> toward each other upon our <hi>diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> Senſes and Judgment of Affairs, wherein we are all concerned th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they be managed aright; and in Charity are to believe no leſs is intend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by moſt. The Deſign of their Publication, is to direct our miſguide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Zeal,</hi> to allay our violent <hi>Heats,</hi> to correct our ſharp and acrimoniou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Humours,</hi> to ſweeten our <hi>Tempers</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſitions,</hi> and mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us better natur'd to one another. That Cauſe which hath Truth an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Righteouſneſs for its Foundations, cannot ſtand in need of any ill Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſupport it; Clamors or Forgeries, paſſionate Tranſports, or malici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous Inſinuations, can do <hi>little Service</hi> to any Cauſe, and <hi>leaſt of all</hi> to the Beſt: by good Will and good Reaſon, by Calmneſs of Temper and force of Argument, when in Conjunction, much may be effected, but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſunited, as good as nothing. The <hi>Matters</hi> whereabout our general Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement is, would not be <hi>fatally</hi> prejudicial to our ſelves or others neither impeach our preſent or future happineſs, did not our <hi>Indiſcretion</hi> in their management, bring in a train of miſchievous conſequences. The <hi>Epidemical Errors</hi> in the Nation are not of a <hi>malignant</hi> Nature, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have they ſeiz'd the Vitals of Religion; I pray God we apply not Remedies worſe than the Diſeaſe. Becauſe we differ from one another with Pride, Self-will, Envy, Affectation, Malice, Paſſion, 'tis no wonder that from theſe Roots of Bitterneſs, ſpring forth thoſe ſowr Fruits of Slanders, Detraction, Lying, Libelling, Aſperſions, Calumnies, Execrations, Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; which are the <hi>Peſt</hi> and <hi>Scandals</hi> of our Age and Nation. It ill becomes a Member of any Church that acknowledgeth <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Head, to be of a <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſition repugnant</hi> unto <hi>his,</hi> to act and be in any other Spirit then that of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Tenderneſs, Ingenuity,</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion, Good-will</hi> and <hi>Beneficence, Univerſal Charity</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> theſe give the Eſſential Form and <hi>Genuine Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to a Chriſtian. By theſe Vertues we <hi>imitate</hi> him whom we <hi>worſhip,</hi> and honour our Redeemer. To whoſe Law of Love if we yield Obedience, 'twill make us better Subjects and Citizens, better Friends and Men than now we generally are: for an entire Submiſſion and Conformity to this Royal Law, makes a good Chriſtian, and <hi>that</hi> a Perſon <hi>ſo</hi> in all Condition and relations</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52929:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Way to Peace By ſome Moderate and Healing PRINCIPLES, PROPOSALS, <hi>and</hi> DIRECTIONS Humbly offered to the Conſideration of all CHRISTIANS, As a MEANS to make us of that PURE and PEACEABLE RELIGION We make Profeſſion of.</head>
            <head type="sub">By one that deſires to be called only by that Holy Name of CHRISTIAN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all matters wherein we diſſent from others, as there are many Caſes both Civil and Religious, which are of a doubtful Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Arguments on both ſides are near an <hi>Aequilibrium,</hi> and we cannot bring the Affair to an Iſſue, to the plenary ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of both parties, whilſt we find thoſe that be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded then we are, to be for the main diſcreet and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and have no apparent reaſon to diſtruſt that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend other then Peace and Right, we ought to be very fair and candid in the interpretation of their differing from us, and make as favourable Allowances as the nature of the thing will admit.</p>
            <p>No Man that will retire a while and uſe his thoughts in calm and impartial Conſiderations, but may eaſily perceive there is no reaſonable account to be given, wherefore he ſhould be diſpleaſed and angry with a perſon that hath different apprehenſions and notions from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for by the Law of Retaliation, the other may pay him in the ſame Coin, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to him again the ſame he meted to him before; becauſe juſt ſo far as the one differs from the other, that other differs from him: ſurely then that fair quarter and ingenuous Conſtructions, I reckon due to my ſelf from anothers hand, I cannot without manifeſt Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Violation of the Law of Charity, refuſe to allow to him.</p>
            <p>He that is enamoured of Truth and Righteouſneſs for their ownſake, and loves them for their innate worth and beauty, and undertakes their defence and patronage, upon no mean and ſiniſter Motives and Inducements, but with an honeſt deſign to promote and vindicate the ſame, will be circumſpect and cautious to manage all his Overtures in order thereunto with that gravity, moderation, ſeriouſneſs, and ſtrength of Argument, that it may appear he endeavours rather to convince his Opponent by Rational Demonſtrations, then vex and exaſperate him by Railleries and Invectives.</p>
            <p>Where the proper means of Conviction, <hi>Viz.</hi> Rational and Moderate Arguing, will not take place and prevail with him that is of a different Notion and Apprehenſion from us, our violent and boiſterous paſſions are uſeleſs and inſignificant; the acting and ſpeaking as if we were tranſported beyond, or were beſide our ſelves, is a very prepoſterous way to bring others to a right underſtanding; 'tis not the ſtrength of our Paſſions but our Reaſons, that can make our Opinions currant and acceptable unto others.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52929:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>All thoſe errors and miſtakes which are imputable to the weakneſs and imperfection of Humane Underſtanding (which was when at beſt, Finite and Fallible) and do not derive a Poyſon and Malignity from the Will, is the onely Source and Original of Moral Evil, have in the judgment of the Wiſer ſort of Men made us rather Patients then Criminals, and juſtly challenge the Compaſſion and Counſel of a Phyſician to adviſe and recover, and not the ſeverity and Sentence of a Judge, to Condemn and Execute; it being more Humane and Chriſtian to deliver a Miſtaken-man from his Errors, then to paſs judgment on him for them.</p>
            <p>The pouring out of our own Blood as a Sacrifice to Truth and Righteouſneſs, if the Providence of God require it, is in it ſelf a more noble and heroick Action, as alſo a more acceptable and grateful Offering to our Redeemer, who was himſelf an Inſtructer, and Inſtance of ſo generous Love and Vertue, then the violent ſhedding of theirs, that contradict and oppoſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>At what a low Ebb is the Divine Life, and with what compaſſionate Reſentments ought we to look on the State of Chriſtianity in the World, when we behold thoſe that profeſs a Religion, wherein is recommended to them by the moſt Endearing Morlves, Patience, Meekne's, Humility, Charity, Peaceableneſs, and mutual forbearing and forgiving one another, and all other Vertues and Graces, which may render Humane Converſation, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally Delightful, and Beneficial; they ſhould as it were in deſpight of all thoſe oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arguments the Goſpel preſents them with, to live in the practice of theſe Divine and Inoffenſive Vertues, be guilty of as horrid Cruelty and Butchery, Envy and Malice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and Uncharitableneſs, towards one another, and that under the pretence of Zeal for this Peaceable and Holy Inſtitution, as the Pagan World can be charged with in their open Wars and Hoſtilities, Strange and Prepoſterous Zeal, to play the Devil (as they ſay) for Gods-ſake, and out of love to Religion, draw out its Vital Spirits, to raiſe and ſubvert theſe indiſpenſable and fundamental fluties of Benignity, Clemency, and univerſal Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, abſtract from which, Religion would be no more to us, then an empty name, and fruitleſs Speculation, and ſignifie nothing either to the Honour of God, or Happineſs of Man. Unhappy Chriſtendom, how art thou degenerated from thy Primitive Purity, Love and Humility, where are the Characters and Impreſſions by which onely it can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear we belong to Chriſt? Doth not the Image and Superſcription we generally bear, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue we do indeed and in truth call another Lord and King.</p>
            <p>Would we diveſt our ſelves of our Paſſions and Prejudices againſt thoſe Perſons or Parties whoſe Opinions and Sentiments we are in oppoſition to, and not engage our private Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Intereſts in our Contentions, nor permit our perſonal and particular deſigns to bias and influence our Motions, the controverting and debating the moſt material points depending in diſpute among us, would be a pleaſant and advantageous Theme, and contribute greatly to the improvement of our judgment and underſtanding, without any diminution of mutual Good-will and Charity.</p>
            <p>In this preſent condition of Weakneſs and Ignorance, wherein none can plead Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from miſtakes, and every man that doth not fit in the Infallible Chair, muſt own he is out and at a loſs ſome where; being ſubject to the ſame Paſſions, and liable to the like Miſpriſſions as others; what is more decorous and becoming thoſe that are under the ſame Circumſtances of a frad and wandring State, than to compaſſionate each others Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Miſapprehenſions than modeſtly to diſtruſt their own Sentiments, than diligently to inquire for further Information, than to attempt others recovery by rational Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not too moroſely to cenſure, not jocouſly to ſport themſelves with the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances and Infirmities of Humanity.</p>
            <p>Thoſe whom we have reaſon to believe from the conſtant Tenour of their Actions prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally deſign God and Goodneſs, although their doubtful Notions concerning ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and yet abſtruſe Truths, hinder them from aſſenting add conſenting to a Form of Words as rigidly true, which by ſome Eccleſiaſtical Determinations and Civil Sanctions, are made the <hi>Shibboleth</hi> to try the Orthodox by, yet if they have ſo much Faith in God through his Son, as to be unto them a Principle of Divine Love and Obedience, their peaceable Diſſent and inoffenſive Converſation, ſhould incline us rather to treat them Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignly and Humanely, than their miſtaken Opinions move us to choller and uncharitable uſage.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52929:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>If once we eſtabliſh this as a Principle that Religion may be forced, there will be no meaſure non end of violence and cruelty; for then in whoſe hands ſoever the Sovereign Power reſides, the Paraſites of it will be inſinuating that it is as Orthodox, as 'tis ſupream; and under the notion of extirpating Hereſie, preſerving Decency, promoting Unity, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the Power of Holy Church, being ſecure againſt its Uſurpations, or ſome plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pretenſions or others, as are moſt ſuitable to advance their Ambitious Projects, the Liberties, the Properties, the Lives of Innocent and Moral Men ſhall be ſacrificed upon the fore-mentioned Principle; and the refuſal perhaps of Subſcription to the moſt unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Propoſitions, be adjudged a Capital Offence, and nothing leſs than life it ſelf allowed to be an Expiation for it.</p>
            <p>Is it not ſad enough for a man fatally to miſtake in the things of his everlaſting Peace, and to err at his own Eternal Peril; but muſt we endeavour to hurry him to the place of torment before his time, and precipitate him before his natural life expire, with all his miſtakes and errors about him, into the Infernal Pit: If his caſe be compaſſionable, which ſlays a man by chance, and he find favour from the Law, ſhall we no much more commiſerate his condition, that through want of skill and judgment miſtakes the way to his own happineſs, and falls into what is call'd Hereſie or Fundamental Error, when he is very careful and induſtrious to decline it.</p>
            <p>It ill becomes Chriſtians to propagate Religion by the Artifices and Methods of <hi>Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxs,</hi> in argues they know not what manner of ſpirit their Saviour was of, that went about doing good, and always Acted in a Spirit of Meekneſs and Humility, and recommended the ſame temper and diſpoſition to his Diſciples; that attempt the Diſſemination of his Doctrine by means ſo contrary to thoſe by which it was firſt planted in the World; our Lord hath promiſed to be always with his faithful Servants in the diſcharge of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt his Church: but this is not accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by humane might and power, but by his Spirit, whereby is given them a Mouth and Wiſdome, which none of the Adverſaries of Truth ſhall be able to reſiſt.</p>
            <p>Confiſcations, Exiles, Interdicts, Inquiſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were ſtrange things in the primitive times of Chriſtianity. He that died for us, gave us no commiſſion to make way for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by force of Arms, the commandment which we had from the beginning was not ſo: This is the Evangelical Doctrine, in Meekneſs to Inſtruct, Exhort, Perſwade, Rebuke, and Beſeech. And if theſe means did fail of their Convincing and Converting Men to the Faith, and they did perſiſt in their Errors, Maugre all the Arguments were offer'd to their minds, to procure their belief of the Goſpel, againſt their Perverſneſs and Obſtinacy to entertain Divine Truth: Chriſt that would have all his Souldiers Volunteers, provided not any Violent and External Remedies; they that refuſed, did it with the hazzard of their Souls, and the Meſſengers had nothing further in Commiſſion when their Doctrine was ſlighted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, then to ſhake off the duſt from their feet, as a Teſtimony againſt thoſe which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves. What kindneſs can Men have for that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whoſe Laws are writ with the point of a Sword, and whoſe Addreſſes to them are in blood and cruelty, which quits the proper <hi>Media,</hi> by which rational Creatures are prevail'd with, <hi>viz.</hi> Reaſons and Arguments, and in lieu of ſatisfying the judgment and underſtanding of the truth of its Propoſitions by concluſive demonſtrations, exacts an implicit belief of them and a blind obecience to them, under the ſevereſt Penalties Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny can contrive.</p>
            <p>Whoever pretends to an Authority over the Religion and Conſciences of Men, and in ſubſerviency to their Salvation, to invade and deſtroy the Civil Rights and Properties of thoſe of the ſame common Family of God with themſelves, ought to ſhow a very plain and authentiquie Warrant by which ſuch power is delegated to them, and that they are conſtituted by the Supream Lord to be his Vicars and Subſtitutes, to demand and recover in his Name the Forfeitures that Infidels and Hereticks make of all their Temporal Felicity, by their unhappy ignorance of the way to Eternal. However men manage and ventilate the Propoſition, That dominion is founded in grace, yet when it comes to be reduced to practice, they are not willing it ſhould paſs for truth any longer then the power continues in their own hands, and they are able to improve it to particular advantage.</p>
            <p>The fancying that our differing Opinions concerning ſome difficult Supernatural Truths, and ſome External Modes of Divine Worſhip, makes us of a different Religion from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52929:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and excludes them that are miſtaken from the benefits of the Covenant and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of God as much as it doth from ours, hath been and is one of the moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ructive Engins by which the peace and happineſs of the Chriſtian Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> undermined; which can never be ſecured ſo long as we account ſuch perſons E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Goodneſs, whoſe belief and practice thwarts ours; the neceſſary and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al conſequence of which, will be rigid Cenſures, and bearing hard upon each other, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nchriſtian and Inhumane Practices.</p>
            <p>I wiſh that great Truth which at laſt God reveal'd to his Apoſtle, was the common Faith of all Chriſtians <hi>Viz.</hi> That God is no reſpecter of Perſons, that he hath no ſpecial regard to any particular Parties and diſtinct Societies of Man, to do for them as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a peculiar Denomination, more then for others; let their profeſſion be never ſo fair and ſpecious, but that in every Nation, in every party, thoſe that fear God and work Righteouſneſs, and thoſe onely ſhall be accepted: 'Tis in vain to expect any Zeal or earneſt Contention to defend or deſtroy any of the Rituals and Outworks of Religion, will be of an advantage to us: whilſt we neglect thoſe indiſputable and indiſpenſable Duties, we cannot but know our Obligations to.</p>
            <p>None of our conteſts for Truth and Religion ſhould make us abandon thoſe mild and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ign Vertues, which are the glory and perfection of it; and when we differ concerning ſuch parts of Chriſtian Faith, which they are not aſſented to, do not render the Goſpel i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tual to attain thoſe great ends whereunto it is deſign'd; if after men have fairly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opos'd the Arguments that oblige them to yield their Aſſent, and moderately heard the Allegations that are offer'd by thoſe of a contrary perſwaſion, both do remain of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer judgment without ſatisfaction from each other, 'tis moſt reaſonable that they part as good friends, and upon as fair terms as they met, and innocently continue their differing Sentiments.</p>
            <p>Few men I doubt give themſelves the trouble of a fair and diligent Examination and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the Articles of their Belief, but either to ſave themſelves the labour of a ſearch, take up their Creed by whole ſale; or for fear of the Event being hazardous, by finding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the trial that the true belief is puniſhable or unfaſhionable, reſolve to continue in and promote the Religion in which they are Educated, though they are not able to render any account either to themſelves or others, wherefore they embrace ſuch Opinions which are handed down to them, then thoſe Arguments which equally ſerve for all Religions alike, and therefore ought not to be uſed for the goodneſs or truth of any.</p>
            <p>No Religion, but 'tis too good to be the Subject of Plays and Farces, and turned into Ridicule and Burleſque. In ſo Profligate and Atheiſtical an Age, 'tis the common concern of all that have Reverence for Deity, and regard to its Revelation, though they differ in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>everal parts and paſſages of it, to keep up the honour of Religion in the main, by diſcountenancing that drolling humour, which under pretence of being Satyrical againſt Hypocrites, doth frequently encroach upon true Piety, and doth by miſtake, at leaſt, to ſay no worſe, wound a Friend inſtead of an Enemy.</p>
            <p>An exact Agreement and Correſpondence in all matters, is ſo far from being abſolulely neceſſary to the happineſs of Humane Nature, that 'tis not Eſſential in the judgment of the Learned, to the Bliſs even of the Angels, of whoſe diſagreement in ſome particulars we have a probable Account in the Hiſtory of <hi>Daniel,</hi> though there is no reaſon to believe it impair'd their Felicity.</p>
            <p>Different apprehenſions, of things diſcreetly and moderately managed, renders converſe more delightful, and our company more acceptable to each other, then it can be where we all know and own the ſame Notion, and all our parts are of the ſame meaſure and proportion.</p>
            <p>The B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll of Contention is kept up, by an haſty and precipitate rejecting other Mens S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſe and Propoſals, and by an over-eager and impatient preſſing of our own; as if what was tendred to us by our Antagoniſt, was not worthy Regard and Conſideration, and what we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>'d ought to be credited without inquiry and rational ſatisfaction. Were this poſitive humour baniſhed out of our common Diſcourſes, together with it we ſhould be quit of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of that inflameable matter which keeps the fire of paſſion and anger, like that of Hell, from going out and ever being extinct.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52929:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>If we enquire after the <hi>Coercive Power</hi> of the Civil Magiſtrate in <hi>Matters of Religion,</hi> and what is the <hi>Adequate Object</hi> thereof, among thoſe who know that it will be employed for <hi>their Intereſt,</hi> they are for making broad its <hi>Phylacteries,</hi> and inlarging its exerciſe and juriſdiction, at leaſt to the utmoſt of its extent. If we conſult others whoſe <hi>Temporal Concernments</hi> are ſubject to be prejudiced by the <hi>Penalties</hi> the Law impoſeth on Diſſenters, they urge, that whilſt they <hi>Worſhip God</hi> in the way which he <hi>preſeribeth,</hi> in a quiet and peaceable manner, no <hi>Humane Power</hi> ought to diſturb and interrupt them, but to grant them its protection, and provide for their ſecurity; but be this as it will, 'tis with me an undoubted Maxime; Let the power wherewith the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is veſted, be never ſo abſolute, 'tis given him for the <hi>Edification</hi> and Benefit, and not the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of his Subjects, and that the condition of Modeſt, Humble, Meek, Peaceable, and innocent Perſons, ſhould be rather better than worſe by the Civil Magiſtrates being of the Chriſtian Religion; and that even they themſelves are not exempted from the Divine commands of Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Lenity, Compaſſion, Condeſcention, Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that theſe Vertues, ſo far as the <hi>Publick welfare</hi> can be preſerv'd, ought to be the <hi>Principal Ingredients</hi> in all their Laws and Conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>We that are of the Proteſtant Profeſſion, at this time eſpecially ought to remember upon what Principles and Motives we forſook the Romiſh Communion; the more firmly to unite us in mutual love, under our ſmaller differences: Some of the Principles, which may be as a foundation to this Union, are: <hi rend="margQuotes">That the holy Scriptures contain in them whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is <hi>neceſſary</hi> to Chriſtian Faith and Manners; That it is a <hi>Duty</hi> incumbent upon <hi>All</hi> to read, to ſearch, and endeavour to find out the ſenſe and meaning of them, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves anſwerably; That whoſoever firmly believes the Divine Authority of the Scriptures, and in <hi>the groſs</hi> all the Truths are comprized in them, though he ſhould mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in ſome particular Truths, his Errors will not, whilſt he is <hi>invincibly and not wilfully ignorant,</hi> prove damnable to him; all that God requires of us in order to our Salvation, being a <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>ſerious endeavour</hi> to know and do his will, and not that we be <hi>impec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable</hi> or <hi>infallible</hi> in this mortal ſtate: That they onely err to their eternal ruin, which oppoſe ſuch Truths they know God hath teſtified; That God hath made nothing <hi>abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary</hi> to Salvation, which is not <hi>plainly revealed;</hi> That no Church of any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar denomination is Infallible, and that general Councils, Synods, Convocations, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and have erred; That the impoſing a Profeſſion of known Errors, and practiſing known Corruptions, is a ſufficient cauſe of Separation; That <hi>publick</hi> approbation makes it but <hi>probable,</hi> that the things they allow and command are good; That the oppoſing my Reaſon and <hi>Authority of Scripture</hi> againſt the <hi>Publick,</hi> is not the oppoſing <hi>my Judgment</hi> againſt it, but that of <hi>God</hi> to that of <hi>Man;</hi> That every man ought to judge for himſelf, which Religion is trueſt; That the Bible is the Religion of Proteſtants, and nothing but that and the plain conſequences thereof, can they with <hi>conſiſtency</hi> to their own <hi>grounds</hi> either <hi>believe</hi> themſelves, or <hi>require</hi> of others; That none ought to take up Truth upon the credit of any, without asking the reaſon why; That he that endeavours to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Scripture in the true ſenſe, cannot be an Heretick; and that it were well if no more then what is <hi>Evident</hi> in Scripture was required to the <hi>Churches</hi> Communion, That the <hi>Rule</hi> to judge Controverſies by, is the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and that no <hi>one Man,</hi> or any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Men, are appointed to judge for the reſt.</hi> Theſe and many other Poſitions of the ſame importance are to be had in the writings of our greateſt and wiſeſt Proteſtants, which if we would diligently improve into practice, would be of excellent uſe to ſweeten our Tempers towards one another, and abate thoſe Annimoſities, Feuds, and malicious Diſſentions, which are the ſhame and ſcandal, and if Heaven prevent not, may be the ruin and deſtruction of our Nation and Religion.</p>
            <p>Love is a Vertue ſo <hi>Amiable,</hi> that it is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> ſpoken well of, and thoſe that are <hi>ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of it to others, deſire it may be <hi>liberally</hi> expreſſed to <hi>themſelves;</hi> in the oppoſite Vices of Malice, Envy, Revenge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> conſiſt not only the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the puniſhment of the next World, but the <hi>foundation</hi> of moſt of the Calamities of <hi>this:</hi> Where this <hi>Divine Grace</hi> with its <hi>Concomitant</hi> Vertues have their Reſidence, there the mind of a man is calm and ſerene, at great <hi>eaſe in it ſelf,</hi> and no way injurious or offenſive unto any; but heartily deſirous that the <hi>whole World</hi> might conſpire in <hi>one common deſign</hi> of promoting each others good and wellfare, and doth not ſtingily and penuriouſly limit, and confine its deſires and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to provide for any <hi>particular Sect</hi> or Party of Men ſo great and plentiful a portion, (nay not his own if he be of any) <hi>that</hi> the <hi>reſt</hi> ſhould <hi>fare</hi> the <hi>worſe</hi> for it; and did this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52929:5"/>Spirit of Univerſal love obtain more generally among men, what a ſtrange alteration ſhould we behold in the World, the <hi>Golden Age</hi> would ſpring up to an inſtant, <hi>Tygers</hi> and <hi>VVolves</hi> would quit their <hi>Sava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneſs</hi> and Cruelty, the <hi>loſt Paradice be reſtored,</hi> and in the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Phraſe, <hi>Inſtead of the Thorn ſhould c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me up the Firr, and inſtead of the Brier the Mirtle; the VVolf would dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard lie down with the Kid, and the Child play on the hole of the Aſpe,</hi> &amp;c. then thoſe black and <hi>Helliſh Paſſions</hi> which <hi>ferment</hi> and fret the Spirits of Men, and render them as <hi>vexatious</hi> and uneaſie to themſelves; as <hi>trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> and <hi>unpleaſant</hi> to thoſe they are <hi>concerned with,</hi> would be <hi>conjured</hi> down to that place of <hi>darkneſs</hi> from which they firſt ſprung, together with that <hi>train</hi> of miſchiefs and plagues which they ſcatter and diffuſe among men.</p>
            <p>The great deſign of Gods ſending his Son into the World, was not to <hi>amuſe</hi> our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, with the propoſing to them <hi>abſtruſe</hi> and <hi>myſterious</hi> Truths, or to perſwade us to yield an Aſſent to Doctrines <hi>knotty</hi> and <hi>incomprehenſible,</hi> to believe, as ſome teach, both againſt ſenſe and reaſon, to gaze upon, and admire not the brightneſs and luſtre, but the <hi>darkneſs</hi> and obſcurity of Divine <hi>Revelation;</hi> theſe muſt needs be ends below ſo merciful and indulgent a Father, and <hi>Inadequate</hi> to ſo great an undertaking as was that of the Redeemer, whoſe Principal Intention, upon the <hi>Propitiation</hi> made for the ſin of the world by the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of himſelf, was to direct mankind to the Practice of the moſt <hi>Generous</hi> and <hi>Godlike Vertues,</hi> and make them partakers of a <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> to recover them from ſenſuality and in dignity, and from <hi>all filthineſs of Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh and Spirit,</hi> to teach them to <hi>deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and Worldly Luſts,</hi> and to <hi>live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly;</hi> to have their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations Honeſt and <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and not to conform themſelves to the guiſe and faſhion of the <hi>degenerate</hi> World; and to incourage them, not ſo much to <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve,</hi> as <hi>do and ſuffer</hi> hard and difficult things, by the expectation of a bleſſed Immortality at his glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Diviſions of the Chriſtian Churches will ſcarce ever be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted, till the <hi>numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cles</hi> which are made <hi>neceſſary</hi> terms of Communion, be <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned,</hi> and the more <hi>ſubtil</hi> and <hi>nice</hi> ones, be accounted as Eccleſiaſtical determinations ought to be; probable and valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not indubitable and <hi>concluſive.</hi> He whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> is in <hi>God</hi> through <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> and makes his Applications and Addreſſes unto the Father in the <hi>Name</hi> and through the <hi>Mediation</hi> and Interceſſion of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> which are the Foundations of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, as it differs from the <hi>Moſaick</hi> and <hi>Natural,</hi> and is ready to aſſent to all Articles of Chriſtianity, which in <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>preſs words</hi> are delivered in the Divine Writings, which are ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>os'd to be the fitteſt, becauſe the Holy Spirit <hi>Dictated</hi> them, who knew beſt in what <hi>Language</hi> thoſe great Myſteries could be beſt <hi>communicated</hi> to our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, is a Chriſtian in the Goſpel ſenſe. 'Tis certain that in matters of pure Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 'tis ſomewhat daring to be wiſe <hi>about what is writ,</hi> to deviate from that Form of found words is of Divine Inſpiration, and o make our Comments and Deductions <hi>equally Authentick</hi> with the Original, for all <hi>Inferences</hi> from Scripture, ſo far as they are but <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> are <hi>Fallible,</hi> and therefore can no further <hi>demand</hi> our <hi>Aſſent</hi> than they <hi>ſatisfie</hi> our <hi>Judgment.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. Smith</note> Thus a learned Author of our own, in his diſcourſe of Propheſie, <q>We muſt not think we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vary Scripture <hi>Expreſſions ſecurely,</hi> with retaining the true meaning, except we likewiſe had as <hi>real</hi> an underſtanding of the <hi>ſenſe it ſelf</hi> as the <hi>Inſpired Perſons</hi> had, over whom God did to far <hi>ſuper-intend</hi> in copying forth <hi>his Truth,</hi> as not to <hi>ſuffer</hi> them to ſwerve from his <hi>meaning.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The greater progreſs we make in Love, by which I underſtand not a <hi>ſingle Paſſion,</hi> but a <hi>Syſtem</hi> and <hi>Conſtellation</hi> wherein are conſpicuous the moſt eminent Vertues, the further <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency</hi> we make in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Goſpel, whoſe very <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Complexion</hi> is little elſe but Love, the <hi>nearer approaches</hi> alſo we make to that great Pattern and Example of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, whoſe <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ps</hi> we are obliged to <hi>tread</hi> in, and to walk in thoſe <hi>Paths of Love</hi> he trod in before us, whoſe will alſo it is that we <hi>tranſcribe</hi> and copy it out in our <hi>Converſation;</hi> this is that <hi>Peculiar Character,</hi> by which Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Diſciples are to be <hi>diſcriminate</hi> from the followers of any other Maſter, and by which his Church may be known from all other Churches: 'Tis obſervable, that though among all the ſigns of the true Church, <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this of Love, yet that <hi>all Faith</hi> is not a more certain ſign of the <hi>True Church,</hi> than want of <hi>Love</hi> is a ſign of the <hi>falſe;</hi> and the ſame is <hi>applicable</hi> to the particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere-ever I find a body of Men, let them <hi>Christen</hi> themſelves with as <hi>glorious a N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as they pleaſe, though they <hi>monopolize</hi> Salvation to themſelves, and <hi>exclude</hi> out of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52929:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Heaven as many as are out of <hi>their Communion.</hi> If I perceive among them bloody and deſtructive Principles, ſavage and violent Actions, boiſterous and ungovernable Paſſions, poyſonous and virulent Humours, helliſh Deſigns and Contrivances, to involve the Peaceable and Innocent in blood and deſtruction; or if they do not boyl up to this height of <hi>overt cruelty</hi> in Actions of a <hi>Sanguine Complexion,</hi> yet if there be found among them a more <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Subtl. Malignity,</hi> a more ſlie and ingenious Artifice to ſpread an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> upon the Credit and <hi>Reputation</hi> of their Neighbours (that are not ſquar'd <hi>exactly</hi> by the <hi>Rules</hi> from which they take their <hi>meaſures</hi> of Truth and Error) by Calumnies and Reproaches, by ſowr Cenſoriouſneſs, by malicious Detractions, by falſe or railing Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I muſt take leave of both theſe kinds in the language of <hi>Jacob</hi> concerning his Two cruel Sons <hi>Simoon</hi> and <hi>Levi: O my ſoul come thou not into their ſecret; unto their Aſſembly my Honour be not thou united.</hi> No profeſſion, though never ſo <hi>plauſible,</hi> no <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions,</hi> be they never ſo <hi>right,</hi> can in his judgment who knows what is the difference between <hi>true Religion</hi> and a <hi>Phariſaick Rightcouſneſs,</hi> be valued any further then they ſubſerve to the Honour and Glory of God on High in promoting Juſtice and Temperance, an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Frame of Mind, a Benign and Charitable Diſpoſition and Inclinations to Peace, and <hi>Good-will towards all Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis to be ſuſpected they have made but a <hi>ſuperficial</hi> ſearch, and ſtudied onely the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>one ſide,</hi> and often neither, in moſt of our preſent Controverſies, that are moſt <hi>dogmatical</hi> and conſident; and though it be granted that they are ſometime on the <hi>ſide of truth,</hi> yet their Orthodox Notions are not truly <hi>the rown,</hi> nor Vertuous and Praiſe worthy, becauſe they are not the <hi>reſult</hi> of a diligent and impartial Enquiry, and an aſſent unto Truth upon <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> Evidence offer'd to their judgment after an <hi>Examination</hi> of ſuch Arguments as are propos'd by the contrary party, which always ought to be thrown into the Scale and <hi>carefully weighed,</hi> before we come to a <hi>piſitive determination</hi> in matters which we would <hi>impoſe</hi> upon <hi>others</hi> Judgment and Practice; but even their right opinions are to be attributed rather to ſuch external occaſions which leave them ſhort of <hi>Rational Truths,</hi> and unbecoming intellectual Agents indued with faculties to ſearch after Truth, as their <hi>fortunate Nativity</hi> where the <hi>right</hi> belief was profeſſed, or <hi>Prepoſſeſſion</hi> from the Principles inſtill'd in their Education, or <hi>incompetency</hi> of parts, to make a through ſcruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or <hi>readineſs</hi> to comply with <hi>Perſons,</hi> they eſteem, care to preſerve heir <hi>worldly Intereſt,</hi> or an <hi>indifferency</hi> whether Religion be true or falſe, and other accidental mouves in conjunction with theſe, which would have made even theſe ſort of men, had the <hi>contrary Tenets</hi> been offer'd to them at firſt on the ſame advantage, been as valiant Champions in the <hi>defence of Error</hi>'s now they <hi>chance</hi> to be of <hi>Truth;</hi> it being not their <hi>integrity</hi> and <hi>ingenuity</hi> and unbiaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> proſecution of Gods will, which gives them <hi>Preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> above others, for in theſe they often <hi>fall ſhort</hi> of their miſtaken Brethren, whoſe <hi>modeſt Enquiries</hi> into the truth of ſome <hi>received Opinions,</hi> may ſometime miniſter matter for ſuſpenſion of belief, and diſſatisfaction in thoſe Notions, which theſe weak and in on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate men do more <hi>readily</hi> aſſent to, and <hi>poſitively</hi> aſſert, becauſe they have not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted themſelves with thoſe <hi>Rational Exceptions</hi> and real difficulties, which others find they are hable to, and intangled withal, which have made a more <hi>narrow</hi> Search and more diligent <hi>Scrutiny</hi> into them.</p>
            <p>That we may the better maintain peace and an amicable correſpondence with thoſe which diſſent from us, we ſhould remember, that in this <hi>ſtate all men</hi> are abnoxious both to Error and to Sin, and <hi>imperfect</hi> both in <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>vertue;</hi> that we ought to put on all mens actions the moſt <hi>favourable conſtruction</hi> their circumſtances will admit; that we our ſelves have at ſome <hi>turns fail'd</hi> as well as our Neighbour; that to take the Chair and Judge in Caſes where <hi>we are parties</hi> and concern'd, is the higheſt injuſtice; that no man ought to be charged with maintaining the ill <hi>Conſequences</hi> of his Opinions, when he doth deny and <hi>diſclaim</hi> them; that <hi>Moral Integrity</hi> recommends a miſtaken man to God, that though he hath provided no <hi>Infallible</hi> preſervatives from Errors, yet ſincere care to avoid them is an <hi>effectual</hi> Antidore againſt their <hi>Poyſon;</hi> and that 'tis <hi>unreaſonable</hi> for us to treat men as <hi>Enemies</hi> for ſuch <hi>Opinions</hi> by which they do not <hi>forfeit</hi> Gods love and <hi>favour.</hi> That, in ſine, What God principally values and requires, is, that Men <hi>ſacrifice</hi> their <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> to him, and yield to him <hi>formal</hi> and <hi>vertual</hi> Faith and Obedience, when they fail through want of ſufficient Information of <hi>Material;</hi> and that if theſe be the terms whereupon God will graciouſly accept his <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>impotent</hi> Creatures, then we ought not to <hi>Reprobate</hi> and <hi>Anathematize</hi> them whom God receives, though they <hi>ſubſcribe</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52929:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>not to all thoſe Articles we have annexed to <hi>our Creed,</hi> and made <hi>fundamental</hi> to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>He which <hi>neglects</hi> not the <hi>means</hi> appointed by Heaven to <hi>inform</hi> him of Truth, but being diveſted of all <hi>worldly reſpects</hi> and ſecret inclinations, that <hi>one</hi> propoſition ſhould be <hi>true</hi> rather than the other, that ſtands <hi>ready</hi> to believe, and <hi>reſolv'd</hi> to obey the Will of God aſſoon as it <hi>appears</hi> to him to be <hi>his;</hi> and as an <hi>upright Judge</hi> with <hi>Caution</hi> and <hi>Impartiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> examines what ever can be alledged to give in Evidence to the Matter he is in queſt of; and as an <hi>Honeſt Chriſtian,</hi> to his Care and Diligence, ſuperadds his Humble and <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prayers</hi> to the Father of Lights for the Divine Influences, and <hi>Concurrence</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> Of Truth, for <hi>his Guidance</hi> and Direction: What ever Error ſuch a Man may hold, what ever Truth he may be unacquainted with upon ſuch a <hi>fair Enquiry,</hi> his miſtake and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is <hi>invincible,</hi> and his caſe <hi>compaſſionable,</hi> and how he ſhall be dealt with at the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Audit, it cannot be <hi>hard</hi> for <hi>them</hi> to judge who partake moſt of the Clemency, Benignity, and Love of the <hi>Father of Mercies,</hi> who <hi>remembers our Frame,</hi> and <hi>knows</hi> that we <hi>are but duſt,</hi> who will make all favourable <hi>Allowances,</hi> and will not upon the <hi>forfeiture</hi> of our Eternal Happineſs, <hi>exact degrees</hi> of knowledge from us above the <hi>Line</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> he hath made, and the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>Faculties</hi> we are indued with; and he that is <hi>conſcious</hi> he hath made the <hi>beſt uſe</hi> of his Underſtanding he is able, in this <hi>Intellectual Employment,</hi> may as well <hi>rejoyce</hi> in the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> though in ſome things he is miſtaken, that he hath ſought the Truth impartially, as he that hath had his <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> in Simplicity and <hi>Godly Sincerity,</hi> may, notwithſtanding ſome <hi>Infirmities</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adtertencies</hi> he hath been ſubject to in his life.</p>
            <p>Though we cannot but own that the <hi>Reformation</hi> both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad</hi> hath ſome <hi>defects</hi> and <hi>blemiſhes,</hi> and is not in all parts compleat and perfect, yet the <hi>progreſs</hi> that hath been made towards it, is a bleſſing ought to be highly valued, and thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and of all perſons <hi>they</hi> ought not to <hi>ſleight</hi> and <hi>vilifie it,</hi> and violently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt about indifferent things, whoſe <hi>lives are not Reformed,</hi> and <hi>ſcruple</hi> not at ſuch things as are <hi>undoubtedly</hi> ſinful; and on the other hand the <hi>Patronage</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> of it is managed to very <hi>little</hi> purpoſe, when undertook by ſuch who take liberty to <hi>vary</hi> from the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> and live not according to the <hi>exact difference</hi> of Good and Evil, and conform not to that <hi>Religion eſtabliſhed by the Law</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and founded in the <hi>Eternal Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of Righteouſneſs, Goodneſs, and Truth. Nothing being more abſur'd and prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous, childiſh and ridiculous, than to be <hi>curiouſly buſie</hi> about the <hi>Publick Reformation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame <hi>work</hi> be done at <hi>home,</hi> nor a truer <hi>Character</hi> of an Hypocrite, than a <hi>forward Zeal</hi> to Correct and Amend the Faith and Religion of <hi>others,</hi> and yet allow <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> in irregular and <hi>diſhoneſt Fractices; to tithe the Mint, Aniſe and Cummin,</hi> with great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs and ſcrupuloſity, and in the interim to neglect <hi>Mercy, Judgment, Faithfulneſs,</hi> and the <hi>weightier</hi> Matters of the Law.</p>
            <p>Theſe would be <hi>happy Signs</hi> of the Chriſtian Churches recovery to a ſtate of <hi>ſteady Peace,</hi> and be a ſpring of true joy to all that are <hi>Friends to real Religion,</hi> to ſee the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt</hi> and Deſign of Chriſtianity proſecuted with as much diligence and induſtry as that of <hi>particular parties,</hi> to ſee our <hi>private Picques</hi> diſcarded, and every <hi>good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man</hi> of whatſoever denomination (in our New Stile) accounted our Neighbour and treated accordingly, to ſee all our Controverſies about <hi>Superſtition</hi> wound upon this <hi>bottom,</hi> that none place <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs Religion</hi> in any thing then the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing will bear, to ſee our <hi>feaveriſh heats</hi> about minute and petty Circumſtances in Worſhip to <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate</hi> and <hi>grow coller,</hi> to ſee us ſo far as we have already attained <hi>to walk by the ſame rule, and mind the ſame thing; and wherein we are otherwiſe minded,</hi> not furiouſly attack and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn one another; but humbly wait on him that hath promis'd that theſe things alſo wherein <hi>we differ he will reveal to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are too prone to believe that the <hi>Ark of God</hi> will fall, unleſs we <hi>ſupport</hi> it with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed hands,</hi> that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church and <hi>Faith</hi> will be prevail'd on by the <hi>Gates of Hell,</hi> except we call for <hi>fire from Heaven</hi> to conſume its Enemies; that <hi>Hereſies</hi> or <hi>Superſtitions</hi> will over-ſpread the Face of the Church, if we run not to an <hi>Arm of Fleſh</hi> and take <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwarrantable Methods</hi> to ſuppreſs and prevent them; but let us contrive as many <hi>expedients</hi> as Humane <hi>VVit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> can execute, to preſerve the Church and Religion from Rents and Diviſions, Ruine and Deſtruction, all our <hi>Attempts</hi> and <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> are likely to prove <hi>Ineffectual</hi> and <hi>Succeſleſs,</hi> which are not founded in <hi>rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52929:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and recommended from a <hi>Spirit of Love, Sweetneſs,</hi> and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus!</hi> When thou comeſt wilt thou find <hi>Love</hi> in the Earth? Did ever any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſtors of a Religion tread ſo <hi>Antipodes</hi> to the <hi>Example,</hi> and walk more contrary to the Precepts of their <hi>Maſter:</hi> It was not becauſe thou wantedſt <hi>Power</hi> but <hi>Will,</hi> that thou didſt not <hi>revenge</hi> the Affronts and Injuries that were offer'd to thy <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Doctrine:</hi> Couldſt thou not have <hi>girded thy Sword upon thy Thigh, O thou moſt mighty,</hi> and <hi>rode on pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly</hi> in the Ruin of thy Enemies, and triumphed over them <hi>in the greatneſs of thy Power?</hi> Hadſt thou <hi>taught</hi> thy Diſciples to <hi>fight,</hi> as <hi>Mahomet</hi> did his <hi>Diſciples;</hi> and in lieu of that <hi>Meekneſs, Live, Gentleneſs, Patience, Forgiveneſs,</hi> &amp;c. which thou requireſt as our <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Tribute,</hi> injoyned us to be <hi>revenged</hi> on Enemies, to <hi>retaliate</hi> injuries, to make way for thy Goſpel, by Rapine and Violence, by <hi>ſeizing</hi> the Properties, by <hi>Invading</hi> the Dominions of thoſe we are able to <hi>prey upon.</hi> Hadſt thou allowed us to <hi>violate</hi> our Faith, to quit our <hi>Allegiance,</hi> to Perſecute, Torment, <hi>Maſſacre our Brethren</hi> to advance thy Kingdom and Power and Glory; then we might have beheld the Deſolations thoſe that profeſs thy Name have made in the World without aſtoniſhment, and owned they had not <hi>forfeited</hi> the Title they Aſſume of being of <hi>the Society of Jeſus,</hi> by incouraging and propagating theſe and ſuch <hi>barbarous Outrages;</hi> which have made good natured Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>afraid</hi> they ſhould <hi>meet</hi> with them again in the other World.</p>
            <p>In the Prophetick Viſion, the Four great Monarchies of this World were repreſented by <hi>Beaſts full</hi> of <hi>Savageneſs and Cruelty,</hi> as oppoſite to the Kingdom of the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> the Glory and Eſtabliſhment of which, was to conſiſt <hi>in Love and Peace, in Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> which although at preſent it obtain not to any <hi>great degree</hi> among Men, yet there are the <hi>Seeds</hi> of this bleſſed and happy Eſtate, ſcatter'd up and down in the Breaſts of <hi>True Believers,</hi> and the <hi>Love of God</hi> and of his <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> is <hi>ſhed abroad in their hearts</hi> by his Spirit, to which the Adminiſtration of <hi>this Kingdom</hi> is committed, which like the ſtone cut out <hi>without hands,</hi> will increaſe by little and little, till it become a <hi>great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and fill the <hi>whole Earth,</hi> as now it doth the Heavens, with its Glory.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Peace</hi> can we <hi>hope</hi> for, ſo long as the ſeveral contending Parties with a kind of <hi>Helliſh Senſuality</hi> careſs and treat themſelves with one anothers Wickedneſs and <hi>Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ties,</hi> and are <hi>abundantly</hi> gratified, that the bounds of Temperance, Juſtice, and Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are tranſgreſſed, or any Villanies though never ſo <hi>hateful</hi> to God, Angels, and all <hi>Wiſe and Good Man,</hi> are perpetrated, provided that the Offenders be of a <hi>different perſwaſion</hi> from them; as if it were an <hi>eligible</hi> and grateful Spectacle to beho'd the <hi>Laws of Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Honour</hi> of his Religion, rendred <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>contemptible</hi> to the World, that we may take occaſion from thence, to <hi>inſult</hi> and <hi>triumph</hi> over ſome we may ſtile our Enemies, and may have opportunity to revenge our <hi>private</hi> Grudges and Quarrels on the Criminals.</p>
            <p>What Peace? So long as this moſt unjuſt and <hi>uncharitable Practice</hi> is kept on foot, whereby the Offences and Extravagancies of <hi>ſome particular Perſons,</hi> are charged upon the <hi>whole</hi> Body or <hi>Corporation</hi> to which they do relate, and the guilt of what is done by <hi>one</hi> in compliance with his <hi>own</hi> Luſts and Paſſions, ſhall be imputed to the <hi>Party</hi> of which he is, as being the natural reſult of their Principles, which if it be <hi>countenanced,</hi> is the moſt <hi>compendious</hi> way not only to <hi>blaſt</hi> the credit and reputation of any <hi>ſmall ſociety</hi> of Men, but will bring the whole Chriſtian <hi>Church</hi> under ſcandal and contempt; as if what <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate ſaid of it was true, That it was a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> to the moſt <hi>flagitious</hi> Offenders and <hi>patroniz'd</hi> thoſe <hi>Vices</hi> to which no other Religion allowed <hi>Expiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Peace can be ſo <hi>long?</hi> that hath not the practice and exerciſe of <hi>Goalineſs</hi> and <hi>Honeſty</hi> for its <hi>Baſis.</hi> Were all our <hi>differences</hi> among our ſelves compos'd to our <hi>mutual ſatisfaction,</hi> and no ſtorms from <hi>abroad</hi> in view to threaten us. 'Tis too eaſie to <hi>prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> how <hi>ſhort</hi> a continuance ſo great a bleſſing may make with us, if we caſt our eyes upon thoſe Vices and Debaucheries, which <hi>reign</hi> among us ſo <hi>uncontroaledly,</hi> which are the <hi>fatal ſymptoms</hi> and ſad preſages of <hi>approaching</hi> judgments. 'Tis not our <hi>Religious</hi> quarrels <hi>alone,</hi> are likely to Shipwrack our Nation, there are <hi>Vices</hi> and <hi>Villanies</hi> of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faner hue, that <hi>increaſe</hi> the ſtorm, and ſeem to render our preſervation and eſcape, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Perſonal Reformation,</hi> impoſ2ible. Were we in earneſt ſo ſollicitous for the Churches and Kingdoms Welfare, as <hi>we ſeem</hi> to be, and had the love for them we pretend, whilſt we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Methods and Arts <hi>others</hi> uſe to <hi>deſtroy</hi> it, we would be more careful
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52929:7"/>our ſelves that <hi>we</hi> did not <hi>promote</hi> its Ruin, and <hi>pull</hi> down its <hi>Pillars</hi> by our own Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salvation,</hi> is of ſuch Eternal Importance, that no man ought to be blam'd for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Inquiry</hi> after the way to it, and for not taking it up on the <hi>Credit</hi> of <hi>another,</hi> who may for ought he knows deceive him, when he can be <hi>ſure</hi> he hath no ill <hi>Deſign</hi> upon himſelf: 'Tis Wiſdoms Direction that our <hi>own</hi> Eyes ſhould look to the <hi>Foundation</hi> on which we ſtand, and that we ſhould not commit our ſelves <hi>blind-fold</hi> to any ones Direction, let them pretend to never ſo <hi>Infallible</hi> Conduct. God hath ſet up a Light in every man; his <hi>Reaſon</hi> is the Candle of the Lord, and to follow it, and follow God, is in the <hi>Old Theology</hi> the ſame; and though this light be complain'd of as <hi>dimn,</hi> yet it being the beſt we have ſince the Fall, 'tis our <hi>ſecurity</hi> to follow it, till we are furniſhed with a brighter; and if we chance to err by going along with our <hi>beſt Friend</hi> and <hi>ſureſt Guid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> our miſtake will not be fatal, becauſe it was not avoidable.</p>
            <p>Tis the Obſervation of a Perſon of Honour who hath uſed both Sword and Shield in the defence of our Reformation from the corrupt Doctrines of <hi>Rome,</hi> That the <hi>Eclicticoi,</hi> who did not <hi>abſolutely believe,</hi> and give up their Judgments to the Doctrines of any <hi>particular</hi> Sect, to be Swayed and Governed by their Principles and Determinations, but upon dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and impartial examining their various and differing Notions and <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mata,</hi> did <hi>reject</hi> what they found <hi>diſſonant</hi> from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and elected and entertained for <hi>Truth</hi> what appeared to them to be agreeable thereto, were reputed a Diſcreet and Honeſt ſort of <hi>Philoſophers:</hi> So for Matters of Divinity there may be, and I doubt not but there is, a Good and Prudent kind of Chriſtians, who do not <hi>zealouſly</hi> eſpouſe and mantain the <hi>Syſtems</hi> and Doctrines of any of thoſe <hi>Diſtinct</hi> Parties whereinto the Chriſtian World is now Crumbled, but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they find the Truth, do <hi>really</hi> Embrace it, and joyn in ſome Truths with one Side and in ſome with another, and receiving the <hi>Truth</hi> in and <hi>for</hi> the <hi>Love</hi> of it, give it the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrence before any other Perſons or Intereſts whatſoever.</p>
            <p>In theſe Notions I have rendred to thy thoughts, I am not alone, but have many of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Reformers of this Church, and of the <hi>preſent</hi> Worthy and Learned Members of it in my company, to whoſe Diſcourſes and Labours I acknowledg my ſelf indebted, which I ther ther mention to ſilence the Clamors and rectifie the miſtakes of two ſorts of men, who on different accounts impute more ſtraitneſs and narrowneſs of Spirit to them, than in Juſtice they ought. Some few expreſſions of this tendency I ſhall recite:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Author of the whole Duty of Man in Cauſe of decayes of Piety.</note> Tis in vain to think Religion can be impos'd by force, that we can <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Wills</hi> and Underſtandings of Men with ſuch <hi>fetters</hi> as we do their <hi>Bodies: Armies</hi> cannot beſiege my <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> nor <hi>Canons</hi> batter my <hi>VVill</hi> The <hi>Logick</hi> of a <hi>Sword</hi> is not proper to induce Aſſent and Conviction: A Chriſtian Perſecutor is a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; The <hi>Goſpel</hi> in one hand, the <hi>Sword</hi> in the other, may make many <hi>Slaves</hi> or <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> but few <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> What motive can I have to receive Religion from an Oppreſſor, can I think that he that treats my <hi>Body</hi> Inhumanely hath a kindneſs for my <hi>Soul;</hi> that he that will not permit me to enjoy my <hi>own,</hi> will help me to any thing is better.</p>
            <p>To theſe I ſubjoyn out of Dr. <hi>H. M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of hearts is better then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in Actions indifferent: The viſible exerciſe of profeſſed <hi>Charity</hi> and kind Forbearance is a more comely <hi>Ornament</hi> of the Church than <hi>conſtrained <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> Opinions, ſuppoſing no venome of a <hi>Perſecutive Spirit</hi> in them, ſhould not <hi>exclude</hi> from the Enjoyments either of publick or private Rights: External force being ſo unfiting in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and moſt of all <hi>unbecoming</hi> the Chriſtian Magiſtrate in matters of Religion, what one may <hi>fancy loſt</hi> by laying aſide perſecution, will be <hi>regained</hi> in as great a meaſure by Peace. Every one that profeſſeth <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the Scripture, let his <hi>Opinions</hi> be otherwiſe what they will, is according to his life worth ability to be prefered, which is abſolutely the moſt <hi>advantageous way</hi> for the advancing the Goſpel and making the <hi>World good,</hi> that the wit of man can find out: The <hi>immediate Dictate</hi> of Conſcience in a Soul which is ſincere is the <hi>Command</hi> of God, and the <hi>Conviction</hi> thereof is properly the <hi>promulgation</hi> of his Will: God ſets a ſincere Religioniſt free in matters of Religion from any external force or power. This Poſition, That <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is not to be granted in Religion, is the the greateſt <hi>injury</hi> and diſintereſt to True Religion can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and brings upon <hi>Nations</hi> Wars, Bloodſhed, Subverſion of Families, Depoſing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Perpetual Enmity and Hatred, and <hi>all the Works</hi> of the Kingdom of Darkneſs; The moſt tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Religions are moſt abhorrent from perſecution for Conſcience ſake; To theſe I might add out of this profound Philoſopher and Chriſtian Doctor; Many more expreſſions of the ſame tenor and importance, were it not ſuperfluous.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52929:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>As a <hi>Coronis</hi> take theſe Propoſitions out of an Author of as great repute for Learning as moſt that have attempted to prove the Proteſtant Religion a Safe Way to Salvation. Mr. <hi>Chill Pag.</hi> 161.</p>
            <p>They are the greateſt <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> who make the way to Heaven <hi>narrower,</hi> the Yoke of Chriſt <hi>heavier,</hi> the Differences of <hi>Faith greater,</hi> the Conditions of Eccleſiaſtical Communion <hi>harder</hi> and <hi>ſtricter,</hi> than they were at firſt made by Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Allow the belief of no more difficulties neceſſary to Salvation <hi>now</hi> than were in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, that no Error is in ſelf deſtructive which was not then: So order Gods Publick Service that plain and honeſt Chriſtians may without hypocriſy, ſcruple, or proteſtation, againſt any <hi>part</hi> of it, joyn in it, then notwithſtanding difference in things <hi>not plain,</hi> and therefore <hi>not neceſſary,</hi> there would be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of <hi>Communion,</hi> Charity and Mutual Tolleration, and by theſe means, Schiſms and Hereſies would be baniſhed the World, and thoſe wretched Diviſions which rend and tear in pieces, not the Coat but the <hi>Members</hi> and <hi>Bowels</hi> of Chriſt, with mutual Pride, Tyranny, Killing, Curſing, and Damning, will receive a bleſſed <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag 177. The Preſumptuous impoſing the <hi>Senſes</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> on the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and laying them on Mens <hi>Conſciences equally,</hi> under Penalty of Death and Damnation; this vain conceit, that we can ſpeak of the <hi>Things</hi> of God, better than in the <hi>Words</hi> of God, the reſtraining the Underſtandings of Men from that liberty wherein Chriſt leſt them, theſe make Schiſms Immortal.</p>
            <p>Take away Perſecuting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for not ſubſcribing to the <hi>Words</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> as the <hi>Words</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> require of Chriſtians onely to believe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to call no man Maſter but <hi>him onely:</hi> Take away Tyranny, reſtore Chriſtians to their <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>full liberty</hi> of Captivating their Underſtandings to Scripture onely, and 'tis to be hoped this will quickly reduce us to Truth and Unity.</p>
            <p>I have learnt, ſaith he, from the Fathers, nothing is more <hi>againſt</hi> Religion than to <hi>force</hi> it; from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that the <hi>Weapons of the Chriſtians VVarfare are not Carnal;</hi> and great Reaſon, for humane violence may make men <hi>counterfeit</hi> but not <hi>believe,</hi> and therefore fit only to breed <hi>Form without,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm within:</hi> 'Tis <hi>unjuſt</hi> to force <hi>VVeak Men</hi> by the Profeſſion of a Religion they <hi>believe not,</hi> to loſe Eternal Happineſs, out of a fear they may poſſibly diſturb the <hi>States quiet,</hi> by Opinions by which neither diſobedience to Authority, or Impiety, is taught or licenſed: They of all men are to be <hi>excepted</hi> from liberty, which teach this <hi>Sanguinary Dactrine,</hi> that 'tis lawful by Humane Violence to enforce others. If Proteſtants did compel others to embrace their Reformation, and offer <hi>violence</hi> to their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> I excuſe them not, and bleſſed had they been, had they choſe rather to <hi>die</hi> for their Religion, than <hi>fight</hi> for it. This way of violence may perhaps produce Uniformity in a <hi>Particular Church</hi> or State, but Immortalize the <hi>greater</hi> and more lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Diviſions of Chriſtendom, maintain perhaps the Profeſſion of Truth in <hi>one place,</hi> and the Oppreſſion in an <hi>hundred.</hi> Thus this great Man hath Writ, who was able by Reaſon and Scripture to maintain his Religion, and not obliged for want of Rational Arguments, to call for the Secular Sword to his Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>I am aware that the <hi>Temper of Mind</hi> hereby recommended, is by many of a <hi>Fiery</hi> and <hi>Active</hi> Spirit decried, and interpreted to ſavour of too great a <hi>latitude,</hi> and to be that luke-warm and <hi>Laodicean</hi> Humour, which is ſo nauceous and hateful with our Lord; That <hi>Truth</hi> is to be proſecuted with our <hi>utmoſt Care</hi> and Intention of Mind, and that we cannot be <hi>too zealouſly</hi> affected in ſo good a Cauſe, but ought to expreſs the greateſt ſervency therein. Although the Enquiry after Divine Truth and the Propagation of it, will juſtifie our greateſt Diligence and Activity, yet it will not account for any <hi>Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> and <hi>Indiſcreet</hi> Actions or Paſſions we ſhall fall into, in the defence and patronage of it; the greater Caution and Prudence is at this time neceſſary to do it <hi>real ſervice,</hi> ſince it hath ſuffer'd ſo much <hi>prejudice</hi> from their <hi>forwardneſs</hi> and heat that have appear'd on its ſide. If I underſtand what it is to be <hi>Zealous</hi> for the <hi>Truth,</hi> 'tis not to be <hi>Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> and <hi>Litigious</hi> about it, 'tis not to give our Natural Tempers, when hot and eager, the ſcope of expreſſing themſelves warmly and contentiouſly for it; 'tis not to charge thoſe that differ from us with <hi>Hereſie</hi> or <hi>Infidelity,</hi> &amp;c. He is the Man that hath a <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> for Truth, that carefully informs his mind concerning it, by <hi>Enquiry</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,</hi> that improves it to <hi>moderate</hi> his Appetites and Paſſions, <hi>to reſine and ſweeten</hi> his Temper and Spirit, to <hi>Correct and Regulate</hi> his Life and Manners, to make his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52929:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Converſe <hi>Beneficial to Men,</hi> and Subſervient to the Honour of the God of Truth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> which the Apoſtles ſo ſmartly reprehended, and warned the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians to avoid, were ſuch that directly tended to the <hi>Subverting Holineſs</hi> of Life, and foſter'd Senſuality and Diſſolution of Manners, and fruſtrated the gracious deſign of God in <hi>Reconciling the World</hi> to himſelf, by the Death and Reſurrection of his Beloved Son, by turning <hi>the Grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, making Chriſt the Miniſter of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, by taking incouragement to ſin becauſe Grace did abound, by abuſing their liberty, to be Servants of Corruption.</hi> To theſe Notions and Practices, St. <hi>Peter</hi> gives the name of <hi>Damnable Hereſies,</hi> and the <hi>Errors</hi> of the <hi>VVicked,</hi> and threatens thoſe with fatal Deſtruction, and <hi>utterly periſhing in their own Corruption,</hi> that ſo taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed.</p>
            <p>But when the Apoſtle hath occaſion to Argue with <hi>VVeak</hi> and <hi>Honeſt</hi> Chriſtians which <hi>held the Head,</hi> and built on the <hi>true Foundation</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, though they were Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and had Miſapprehenſions concerning the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Indifferent</hi> Things and Truths of the <hi>leſſer Magnitude,</hi> he doth not ſeverely animadvert on them, nor was he willing to be poſitive and lay reſtraints on their liberty, that he might not, as he ſpeaks, <hi>caſt a Snare upon them,</hi> nor confine them where Chriſt had left them free; but gives them general Rules to obſerve, that Love and Peace might be maintained in the free uſe of their Chriſtian Liberty, and that they might manage it ſo as that it become <hi>not a ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Block</hi> to them that <hi>were weak,</hi> as that <hi>they wounded not their brethrens weak conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> by their imprudent exerciſe of it; and that they ſhould not <hi>deſpiſe</hi> or <hi>judge</hi> one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, but that they ought <hi>to bear one anothers burdens,</hi> and not <hi>ſo much to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as every one to pleaſe his Neighbour for his good Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not difficult to inſtance a great many Caſes, where <hi>common Prudence</hi> and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity will make <hi>Allowances,</hi> if not <hi>Apologies</hi> for Erroneous Apprehenſions, as where there are not <hi>evil conſequences</hi> attend them, where there is no <hi>Malignity</hi> and <hi>Ill-will</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with them, where the miſtakes may reſult from the <hi>Prejudices of Education,</hi> or be founded in <hi>Natural Temper</hi> and Conſtitution, where there are no <hi>Indications</hi> of Pride and <hi>Affection,</hi> where the <hi>injury</hi> and dangers of his Errors will be to <hi>himſelf</hi> and not to other perions, where there have not been <hi>opportunities</hi> for better information, where men of known <hi>Integrity</hi> and Ability are of <hi>different</hi> Perſwaſions, where <hi>Expreſſions</hi> are <hi>Ambiguous</hi> and fairly capable of a two-fold ſignification, where to a <hi>particular</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake is ſuperadded a <hi>general belief</hi> of the Truth, or compenſation made by Uniform <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> and Univerſal <hi>Charity,</hi> where the <hi>Cenſor</hi> hath great reaſon to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> his <hi>own</hi> judgment, being compounded of the <hi>ſame frail</hi> and deceivable Materials as others are and is Obnoxious to the ſame, and poſſibly may be <hi>Actually intangled</hi> with greater Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors than his, whom he animadverts upon: I am apt to believe that whoſoever ſhall ſerio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly attend unto theſe and ſuch like Caſes, for 'tis not poſſible to inſtance <hi>All,</hi> which <hi>challenge</hi> our <hi>Candour</hi> and good Conſtruction, will not be raſh and harſh in his condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cenſuring ſuch, whoſe Notions and Tenets are <hi>not agreeable to his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thy Brother judge not according to thy <hi>ſenſe,</hi> what can that be to thee to move thy Spleen and Paſſion? Hath he not a Maſter of his <hi>own</hi> to ſtand or fall to, hath he not a <hi>Right</hi> to judge for himſelf as well as thou haſt, and may he not uſe it without <hi>thy leave?</hi> Is not <hi>Premeditation</hi> neceſſary to make a <hi>wiſe choice</hi> and give <hi>true Judgment?</hi> Why then ſhould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt thou be impatient that he will not <hi>immediately accord</hi> with thy Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, but co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſider before he determine? May it not be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable</hi> to believe he hath not a <hi>fair Appearance</hi> of Truth and Show of Reaſon on his ſide, which lead him out of the way? And if it be ſo, 'tis moſt unreaſonable to oblige him to <hi>alter his Opinions,</hi> till thou haſt propos'd <hi>ſufficient Evidence</hi> to his Underſtanding, that he may ſee a <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> ſo to do: for ſuch is the frame and conſtitution of our <hi>Humane Faculties,</hi> that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe as <hi>we list,</hi> take up Notions, and admit them to <hi>credit at our will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> without the Evidence of Reaſon, nor quit and <hi>diſcharge</hi> our ſelves from them, when we <hi>are minded it</hi> ſhould be otherwiſe, without Arguments and <hi>Rational Inducements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an Evil incident to moſt, and the rather becauſe few charge themſelves with it in point of Conſcience, <hi>Viz.</hi> an <hi>Eaſie Credulity,</hi> or <hi>Over-haſty</hi> taking up III Reports of Men without <hi>ſufficient grounds;</hi> and then ſpreading them, and deſcanting on them as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52929:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>true,</hi> this now is not onely <hi>Prejudicial</hi> to <hi>Humane Converſe,</hi> as alienating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ens Affections from each other; and tending to the ruin of more perhaps then only a Mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>od Name and Reputation, but muſt be of great concernment to our <hi>own Peace</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atisfaction of Mind, if we have any <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity</hi> left; for if through this eaſineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> belief we are miſtaken, and diſperſe the lie, what <hi>Anſwer</hi> can we give <hi>our ſelves,</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reflect on the ſcandalous Imputations and falſe Cenſures we have paſſed on an Innocent.</p>
            <p>Prithee tell me what advantage thou lookeſt for, by being diſtinguiſhed from others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>Ritual Obſervances,</hi> by <hi>ineffectual Opinions,</hi> by <hi>different Deneminations,</hi> by <hi>External Formalities,</hi> by a fondneſs for them, and for <hi>thy ſelf</hi> too, that thou paſſeſt under a <hi>Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uliar</hi> Character, on that account, when in the mean time thy <hi>Deportment</hi> and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is not <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from the reſt of the World, but <hi>ſavors</hi> of the ſame Earthly, Senſual, Proud, Carnal, and Selfiſh Deſigns and Intereſts as <hi>theirs.</hi> God is not ſo much beholding to Men as they vainly imagine, for their attempts to advance <hi>that Kingdom which conſiſts but in Meats and Drinks, and the like, and cometh with Obſervation,</hi> and hath onely an External Viſible Pomp and Grandeur to ſet it <hi>off</hi> withal; and is at beſt Artificial and Mechanick. The Throne wherein he deſires his <hi>Empire and Dominion</hi> ſhould be eſtabliſhed, is the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> of man, and if that be not entirely ſubdued to the Divine Authority, and if <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> do not <hi>triumph</hi> there, all other <hi>Formal Submiſſions and Profeſſions</hi> that are ſolemniz'd, do in earneſt ſignifie nothing to the Honour of Gods Sovereignty, whoſe Kingdom doth not <hi>come with Power and Glory</hi> till <hi>his Will be done in Earth, as 'tis done in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis high time to take our Saviours Council to go home and learn, <hi>Viz.</hi> retire into our ſelves, and conſider what this meaneth, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> that we may at length proportion the <hi>degrees</hi> of our Zeal and Affections to the <hi>true Nature</hi> and State of things, and no longer make ſuch <hi>Partial Preferences</hi> as hitherto we have done, ſpending our <hi>main ſtrength</hi> in the defence of the <hi>Out-works,</hi> whilſt the chief <hi>Cittadel</hi> through negligence falls into the Enemies hands; attending with great diligence to the <hi>outward Forms</hi> and Mode <hi>of Religion,</hi> while the <hi>inward Life and Power</hi> decays and languiſhes for want of due Proviſion. This <hi>Over-valuation of Externals,</hi> hath given a fatal check to the progreſs of True Religion in the World, and diverted the generality of Men from the proſecution of thoſe <hi>Divine</hi> and Excellent <hi>Vertues</hi> wherein the very <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of it conſiſt, which are both of greateſt concernment and benefit unto Men, and glory and honour unto God: for whilſt they have <hi>inverted</hi> Gods Order, and <hi>prefer'd Sacrifice</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mercy,</hi> and put the <hi>Means</hi> in the <hi>place</hi> of the <hi>end,</hi> what God Inſtituted and Ordain'd to be <hi>Subſidiary,</hi> to promote Religion, hath been perverted and abuſed to <hi>Obſtruct</hi> and <hi>Impede</hi> it.</p>
            <p>True Religion conſiſts in <hi>Love, Holineſs, Righteouſneſs, Humility, Sincerity, Sobriety, Meekneſs,</hi> and the like Divine Graces; and for Deficiency in theſe God makes no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances; glorious things are ſpoken of theſe and all <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> of God: much more <hi>Inventions</hi> of Men, when they come in <hi>Competition</hi> with them, are of little or no <hi>Valuation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>Indiſpenſably</hi> neceſſary and <hi>Eſſentially</hi> requiſite, to qualifie and diſpoſe us for the enjoyment of God and Happineſs; they are of a <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Eternal Right,</hi> Writ by the Finger of God in the mind of Man, in the firſt moment of his Creation; theſe make us conformable to our Creator, like to our Father, renew his Image in us, and make us according to our Meaſure and Proportion <hi>partakers</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature.</hi> Theſe render us acceptable to God, and reſtore us to his Favour; they are the true Enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blements and Embelliſhments of the Soul, they have not an <hi>Arbitary Goodneſs</hi> depending onely on the <hi>reſolution</hi> of the <hi>Divine</hi> Will, but an Inherent and <hi>Intrinſick</hi> Excellency <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential</hi> to them. All <hi>Inſtituted</hi> Worſhip is appointed to Miniſter to theſe, the deſign of our Lords undertaking was to promote them, the Treaſures of his Kingdom are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to them, our own and others Peace is ſettled and preſerv'd by them, and againſt theſe there is no Law no Objections. He that in theſe great things of Religion <hi>ſerveth Christ, will be acceptable to God and approved</hi> of all Wiſe and Good men.</p>
            <p>Theſe challenge our moſt earneſt Zeal and Intention, our greateſt Fervency and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, our conſtant care and diligence; but alas we take it it to be too heavy a burden to charge our ſelves with theſe weighty things of the Law and Goſpel, and therefore that we may the more quietly eaſe our ſelves of them with as few rebukes from our Conſciences as we can, we create refuges of lies, to which we repair for ſhelter againſt their Importunities and Convictions, to which Sanctuarys not only the more Demure and Phariſaick, but the Publican and Profaner Sinners do reſort; and as a Supplement to their defects in Morals, and Compenſation for Vicious Practices, expect to render God Propitious to them by ſome modes of Devotion, ſome ſcheme of Opinions, ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52929:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Forms of Godlineſs, ſome Sanctimonions Shews, by Communion with the Church, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> frequenting Ordinances, by Zeal againſt others Sins and Errors, by Acting ſome ſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, by abhorring ſome ſingle Vice, by <hi>paſſionate</hi> Conteſts for <hi>Publick</hi> Uſages or <hi>Particular</hi> Perſwaſions, by bearing hard upon thoſe that diſſent from them, either by <hi>Cenſure</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> and by believing thereby <hi>they do God good ſervice;</hi> ſome one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other of theſe or the like <hi>formal Artifices,</hi> or elſe ſome <hi>more Spiritual</hi> and Refined Pieces of Hypocriſie, <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>Luſts</hi> and Paſſions and Intereſts of Men, have almoſt beniſhed out of the World that Religion which is <hi>Pure, Peaceable, Gentle, caſie to be Intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, without Partiality, and without Hipocriſie,</hi> and made us forget there is a Text in the Bible dehorts us from <hi>all Bitterneſs and Wrath and Anger, and Clamour, and Evil-ſpeaking, with all Mallee;</hi> and though we may flatter our ſelves vvith a couceit, that theſe Vices with others of the ſame kinds may be <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niv'd</hi> at and <hi>diſpens'd</hi> vvith, vvhen they are turn'd againſt the <hi>Enemies</hi> of God, and his Church, State, or People, yet ſuch is their <hi>Natural Malignity,</hi> and Turpitude, that they cannot be <hi>Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi'd</hi> and Authoris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by any <hi>Power</hi> or Prerogative in Heaven or Earth.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that vvould be <hi>Dictators</hi> in Religious Affairs, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire</hi> in Matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if they deſign to bring it to a good Iſſue, ought to be themſelves very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable in their lives, and do thoſe things may gain a belief that <hi>God</hi> vvill not <hi>refuſe</hi> to have <hi>familiarity</hi> with them, and acquaint them with his Will. What <hi>Credit</hi> can be given to their <hi>Report</hi> of God, that are <hi>Enemies</hi> to him <hi>in their Minds by Wicked Works?</hi> Who can look for a <hi>true Character</hi> of God, from one that bears not his <hi>Image?</hi> For right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of him and his ways from one that is a ſtranger to both? <hi>Truth</hi> is moſt likely to be found in <hi>Conjunction</hi> with <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> Wickedneſs <hi>Corrupts</hi> and Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es the <hi>Principles</hi> of the Mind; the <hi>Faculties,</hi> by which M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſhould make <hi>Right Judgment</hi> of Religion, are <hi>deprav'd</hi> by Pride and Luſt. Where theſe are Predominant in the Lives and Actions of Men, vve may juſtly ſuſpect their <hi>Acquaintance</hi> vvith Divine Truth, and their <hi>Ability</hi> to Conduct and Guide others thereinto. Did his <hi>Holmeſs,</hi> ſo call'd, really deſerve that Name, ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantly aſſumed and attributed, I ſhould not wonder that he was <hi>Conſulted</hi> as an <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle.</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> were united. Till the Soul be hallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and puriſied from corrupt Paſſions and terrene Affections, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> will not vouchſafe to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten</hi> it. In Heaven, where there are the <hi>fulleſt Communications</hi> of <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> there are the cleereſt and brighteſt <hi>Minifeſtations</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truth is moſt likely to be found where the Author of it was, nor in the ſtrong Wind, nor in the Earthquake, nor in the Fire; not in minds ſuriouſly Agitated with their own Paſſions and Appetites, but in the <hi>ſtill ſmall voice;</hi> in thoſe of a Sedate, Calm, Benign, Quiet, and compoſed Temper: Truth and Love are naturally allied, and ſeldome part compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he that treads the Paths of Love and Peace, doth rarely err from the way of Truth. He of whom 'tis ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he <hi>is Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht,</hi> 'tis alſo he is <hi>Love.</hi> He whoſe Character is a Deceiver and Liar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>Apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> too; a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>derer and deſtroyer.</p>
            <p>We all wiſh for Peace, and ſay we prize it, we complain that Earth is almoſt an Hell for want of it, that Fury, Paſſion. Violence, are the ſame in the <hi>Rational</hi> World, as Storms and Tempeſts in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural;</hi> and we profeſs we are ready and willing to do our utmoſt to allay theſe by Kindneſs, Love, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency; but when the matter comes to the Teſt, our Actions ſpeak we are of another mind, we inſiſt then on ſuch terms as render all Union and Accommodation impoſſible; we are <hi>Peremptory</hi> and <hi>Inflexible</hi> in our <hi>Notions,</hi> and exact the <hi>utmost</hi> of our Brethren, without allowance or abatement; and as Victorious and Succeſsful Princes, will not refuſe Peace, yet not accept of it neither; on any other conditions then our ſelves propoſe. Thus the means of compoſing our Breaches, have rent them the wider, and whilſt the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> is laid <hi>too narrow</hi> and ſcanty for that vaſt <hi>Superſtructure</hi> 'tis to ſupport, it cannot be expected to be with any other ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>We are not <hi>Originally</hi> diſaffected to one another, the ſtate of Nature before mans Apoſtacy was peaceable, the diſſention of Brethren was the <hi>Effect</hi> of Mans <hi>Praevarication</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſection</hi> from God; and is it not realonably to be expected, that the nearer approaches we make to our <hi>Primitive I aegrity,</hi> the more that Benign and Loving Temper and Spirit ſhould revive and flouriſh among us, which preſerved <hi>Paradice</hi> it ſelf from a <hi>Chaos</hi> and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>Our Diffentions caſt a diſhonour on the Head of our Recovery, as if he could not accompliſh the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his Undertaking; and reſtore and create Man a-new to that <hi>Love</hi> and Friendſhip which was <hi>Natural</hi> to him before he revolted from his Innocence and Allegiance to his Creator.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Charity is the true <hi>Panacaea</hi> or All-heal, I mean not that ſelfish Charity which behaves it <hi>ſelf ſo unſeemly,</hi> as to begin at home and end there too, or elſe ſteps out of doors onely to its own or Neighbouring Party, and Limits and Contracts its Beams to a ſingle Point; but that diffuſive and extenſive Grace, which is of an Univerſal Latitude and Comprehenſion, that takes a large Sphere, for Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Motion; this is the great Security and common Preſervative of the Peace of Mankind, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it no <hi>Guaranty</hi> can prevent Infractions and Breaches being made upon it: Than this the Apoſtle could not shew a <hi>more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>lent may;</hi> and if this be not ground firm enough to caſt Anchor on to preſerve us from that Shipwrack with. which we are threatned from our preſent Unchriſtian Storms; I pray God direct thoſe whom it moſt concerns, to that which may be ſo.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
